<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009-03-15</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="nines">rce236</idno>
            <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.236</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Stirling Library, University of London, SL V.28. Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections From the Letters of Robert
               Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 40–43; and Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
               (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 320–321 [in part; misdated July 15. 1799].</p>
            <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
            <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
            <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Southey’s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
               <category xml:id="people">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
               <category xml:id="places">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
            <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
            <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>corrections from proofing</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>TEI Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="236" type="letter">
            <head>236. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1797-07-19">19 July 1797</date>
               <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 4. Bedford Square/
                  London<lb/>Stamped: RINGWOOD<lb/>Postmark: AJY/ 20/ 97<lb/>Endorsement: 1797 No 4/ Robert Southey/ Burton 19 July/ rec<hi rend="sup"
                     >d</hi>: 20 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 22 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  <lb/> MS: Stirling Library, University of London, SL V.28. ALS; 4p.<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title level="m"
                     >Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 40–43; and Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 320–321 [in part; misdated
                  July 15. 1799].</note>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <address>
                     <placeName>
                        <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>.</placeName>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1797-07-19"> July 19. 1797.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> My dear friend I sincerely thank you for your letter. its contents are strange &amp; I am inclined to think when <ref
                  type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> blamed me for not doing my utmost to relieve my family he must have
               alluded to my repeated refusal of entering into orders; a step which undoubtedly &lt;would&gt; have almost instantly relieved them
               &amp; which occasioned me great anguish &amp; many conflicts of mind. To this I have been urged by him &amp; by <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>, but you know what my religious opinions are, &amp; I need not ask you whether
               I did rightly &amp; honestly in refusing.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Till Xmas last I supported myself wholly by the profits of my writings. when I left Lisbon I had thirty pounds from
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, of which a large part was expended in paying my passage &amp;
               the journey home. When my determination was made not to enter into the church I instantly quitted the University, that <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> might no longer be inconvenienced by me. I applied for a clerks place in a
               public office &amp; my republican principles occasioned my ill success. at this time my acquaintance with <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> commenced; I had all the enthusiasm which a young man of strong feeling
               &amp; an acute sense of right &amp; wrong can possess, &amp; resolved to go to America &amp; attempt to establish a better system. we
               hoped to raise a sum sufficient amongst us, &amp; I had then expectations that the reversion of a family estate might be sold, which
               has since proved worth nothing. wild as the plan was it wanted not plausibility &amp; <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> would have gone with us had it taken place. at the end of 1794 I found myself
               disappointed in this; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> with whom I had previously lived had turned me
               out of her doors; &amp; I would not be burthensome to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> tho my
               quitting her was against her wishes. I went to Bristol to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
               &amp; supported myself &amp; almost him I may say, for what my labours earned were as four to one. I gave lectures, I wrote
               indefatigably. nor is there one single action of this whole period that I would wish undone.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> One <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">friend</ref> I had, only one, willing &amp; able to serve me; but
               he had not the power till he was of age. in the summer of 1795 <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, as
               you know, came to England, he urged me very strongly to take orders. my heart was heavily afflicted: my literary resources were
               exhausted, &amp; it was yet a year &amp; half before my friend could assist me, &amp; you will believe &lt;me&gt; when I say that my
               spirit could but ill brook dependance. <del rend="strikethrough">I</del> Add to this that my opinion of <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">S T Coleridge</ref> was not what it had been, for by long living with him I knew much of
               his character now. I gave him <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> letter when it arrived &amp; told him
               I knew not what I ought to do. I wrote to my friend — he strongly advised me against the church &amp; recommended the Law when he could
               enable me to pursue it. after some days I followed this advice; our <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxx xx xxxx</del> finances no longer
               suffered us to remain at Bristol as we had done, we removed as we had before agreed, I to <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref>, <del rend="strikethrough">&amp; bef</del> our arrears were paid with twenty
               guineas which <ref type="m" target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> advanced as the copy right price of the poems which were
               published not till after my return from Lisbon. during all this <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"
                  >Coleridge</ref> was to all appearance as he had ever been towards me — but I discovered that he had been employing every possible
               calumny against me &amp; representin me as a villain.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">My mothers</ref> was now my home, but I was more frequently with <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>, &amp; with a mind agitated by so many feelings did I compose the greater part of
               Joan of Arc. when this was nearly compleated <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> asked me to go abroad
               with him. I consented, &amp; married the morning of my departure. this too requires some explanation. I had never avowed a<del
                  rend="strikethrough">n</del> long formed attachment till the prospect of settling in America made me believe it justifiable. I
               placed <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> during my absence with <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Cottles sister</ref>, who keep a school, as one of their family, &amp; it was not proper that she
               should be supported by me except as my wife. the remainder of what Joan of Arc was to produce would defray this expence. on my return I
               &lt;had&gt; resolved still to leave her there, &amp; live seperately till the Xmas of 1796 when I had no evil to endure — but
               dependance.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I returned however with the remainder of the thirty pounds — about 18 I believe. I had likewise the matter for my
               Letters, which were only published from necessity. <ref type="m" target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> supplied me in advance
               with such small sums as I wanted from time to time, which the sale of the first edition of that book would repay, &amp; my own reserved
               copies of Joan of Arc produced me <del rend="strikethrough">with thes</del> enough with these assistances. By Xmas I had published my
               poems &amp; letters.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797) and <title level="m"
                     >Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797).</note> &amp; in the course of the following month
               received the first quarterly payment of an annuity of 160£.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Had this been without the heavy incumbrance of such obligation I would have taken a cottage, &amp; lived there with my
               wife &amp; mother, without one wish unsatisfied. as it was, it was my duty to labour till I could do this indepently by the Law. we had
               clothes to purchase — some little to discharge — &amp; a journey to London. with these draw-backs you will easily conceive that at [MS
               torn] the end of the first half year nothing could remain.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> It is only two days since I have learnt that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> had any
               obligations to the D. of N.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified, but the abbreviation suggests an aristocrat, perhaps a
                  Duke.</note> &amp; what that obligation was I knew not till your letter informed me. <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> wrote to me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer"
                  >Thomas</ref>, said he had desired Burn<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Burn (dates unknown) was attached to the
                  British Factory, Lisbon.</note> to send me ten pounds — that he would supply me with money from time to time — &amp; requested
               therefore to know the state of my finances. this surprized me because I had told him what I expected. on the receipt of this letter I
               wrote to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> &amp; told her to expect this ten pounds, which I
               fortunately wanted not, for this purpose I wrote to Burn for it by means of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer"
                  >Thomas</ref>, explaining to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> why I accepted it that he might not
               think I was wantonly draining <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>. this I shall explain in my letter to
               Lisbon which fortunately is not yet written.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Thus you may see that the only means I have <del rend="strikethrough">omitted</del> ever possessed of assisting <ref
                  type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> was by entering the Church. God knows I would exchanged every
               intellectual gift which he has blest me with for implicit faith to have been able to do this. I have urged her to come &amp; live with
               me; she has a large lodging house which does not pay its own rent, &amp; my wish is that she would let the remainder of her lease upon
               a reduced rent, <del rend="strikethrough">that what</del> &amp; sink a certain little to prevent greater loss. I can then support
               her.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I care not for the opinion of the world, but would willingly be thought justly of by a few individuals. I labour at a
               study which I very much dislike, to render myself independant — &amp; I work for the booksellers whenever I can get employment that I
               may have to spare for others. <del rend="strikethrough">I now do all I can</del> I sent ten pounds when last in London to <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Ediths mother</ref> whose wants were more pressing than those of my own. I now do all I can,
               perhaps I may one day be enabled to do all I wish. however there is One who will accept the will for the deed.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you.</salute>
               <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
