<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
                </author>
                <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor, </resp>
                    <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor, </resp>
                    <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor, </resp>
                    <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
                    <name>Laura Mandell</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2009-03-15</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="nines">rce229.1</idno>
                <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.229.1</idno>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                        unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                        1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                        only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                        redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
                        <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
                    </p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                        <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                            Circles.</item>
                        <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
                    </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                        that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                        additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                        all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23. Not previously published.</p>
                <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
                <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
                    Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
                    Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
                    Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
                    Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
                    Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
                    Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
                    Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
                    Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
                    the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
                <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
                    Nottingham Trent University.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
                    <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Southey’s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
                    <category xml:id="g1">
                        <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g2">
                        <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g3">
                        <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g4">
                        <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g5">
                        <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g7">
                        <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g6">
                        <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g8">
                        <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g9">
                        <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g10">
                        <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g11">
                        <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g12">
                        <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g13">
                        <catDesc>History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g14">
                        <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g15">
                        <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g16">
                        <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g17">
                        <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g18">
                        <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g19">
                        <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g20">
                        <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g21">
                        <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g22">
                        <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g23">
                        <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g24">
                        <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g25">
                        <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g26">
                        <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g27">
                        <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g28">
                        <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g29">
                        <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g30">
                        <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g31">
                        <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g32">
                        <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g33">
                        <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g34">
                        <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
                    <category xml:id="people">
                        <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
                    <category xml:id="places">
                        <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
                <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
                <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#AB" when="2014-12-01" n="4">
                <label>Changed by</label>
                <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
                <list>
                    <item>New Letter coded and added</item>
                </list>
            </change>
            <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="5">
                <label>Changed by</label>
                <name>Laura Mandell</name>
                <list>
                    <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
                </list>
            </change>
            <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
                <label>Changed by</label>
                <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
                <list>
                    <item>corrections from proofing</item>
                </list>
            </change>
            <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
                <label>Changed by</label>
                <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
                <list>
                    <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
                </list>
            </change>
            <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
                <label>Changed by</label>
                <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI Encoding</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div n="229.1" type="letter">
                <head>229.1 Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref> [fragment], <date
                        when="1797-06-30">[late June 1797?]</date>
                    <note resp="editors" place="foot" type="headnote">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp.
                        29&#8211;30.<lb/> Dating note: the letter was probably written in late June 1797, shortly after Southey left London for
                        Hampshire on 22 June.</note></head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline><address><placeName> <ref target=" places.html#ChristChurch">Christ Church</ref></placeName></address> [No
                        date]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>.&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;I went to the Chapter
                    Coffee-house Club. <note n="1" resp="editors" place="foot">Chapter Coffee-house in Paternoster Row, near St Paul&#8217;s Cathedral
                        in London. As Paternoster Row was the site of many publishers and booksellers, the Coffee-house became a meeting place for
                        writers and all those involved in the book trade. Visitors could make use of the wide collection of books and newspapers held
                        at the Coffee-house for a small subscription. A small Club was meeting in the Coffee-house at this time to discuss literary
                        and scientific topics. George Dyer was a prominent member. Southey accompanied Thomas William Carr (1770&#8211;1829),
                        solicitor to the Board of Excise, and the Nonconformist Minister, Rochemont Barbauld (1749&#8211;1808), there on 9 February
                        1797; see <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 39.</note> A man
                    read an essay upon the comparative evils of savage and civilised society; and he preferred the first because it had not the curses
                    of government and religion! <note n="2" resp="editors" place="foot">The man was Morgan (otherwise unidentified) and his story was
                        intended &#8216;to prove that the old age of the American savage is not destitute and miserable&#8217;, <title>Common-Place
                            Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 39.</note> He had never read Rousseau. What
                    amused me was to find him mistaken in every fact he adduced respecting savage manners. I was going to attack him, but perceived
                    that a visitor was expected to be silent. They elected me a member of one of these meetings, which I declined. &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">A friend of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref> has been uncommonly kind to me
                    &#8211; <ref target="people.html#MontaguBasil">Basil Montague</ref>. He offered me his assistance as a special pleader, <note
                        n="3" resp="editors" place="foot">A lawyer who specialised in drafting statements of case, rather than appearing in court or
                        giving legal opinions.</note> and said, if he could save me 100 guineas, it would give him more than 100 guineas&#8217; worth
                    of pleasure. I did thank him, which was no easy matter; but I have been told that I never thank anybody for a civility, and there
                    are very few in this world who can understand silence. However, I do not expect to use his offer: his papers which he offered me
                    to copy will be of high service. Tell <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> this.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">I commit wilful murder on my own intellect by drudging at law; but trust the guilt is partly expiated by the
                    candle-light hours allotted to Madoc. <note n="4" resp="editors" place="foot">Southey&#8217;s first full draft, written in
                        1797&#8211;1799, of his epic <title>Madoc </title>(1805).</note> That poem advances very slowly. I am convinced that the best
                    way of writing is, to write rapidly, and correct at leisure. Madoc would be a better poem if written in six months, than if six
                    years were devoted to it. However, I am satisfied with what is done, and my outline for the whole is good. &#160; &#160; &#160;
                    &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;.</p>
                <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you.</salute>
                    <salute rend="indent3">R.S.</salute></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
